The final advantage of fragments, doesn't involve user interfaces at
all. As you know, as visual components, activities are destroyed and
re-created, whenever the device configuration changes. Most notably, when the
screen orientation switches. That makes sense, because there's a good chance
we'll want to create a different layout, to better suit the
new configuration. But if we can use fragments to break up
visual activity modules, and find out logical ones as well,
it turns out we can do exactly that. And because these
fragments are non-visual, there's no need to recreate them
every time the UI needs updating. Within the onCreate
handler of your non-UI fragment, call setRetainInstance, passing in
true, and return null in your onCreate view handler.
Then, once the parent activity is created, you can
kick off any connections, threads, or tasks that are
bound to the lifetime of the activity, which don't
need to be interrupted every time the device rotates.